Guide to the Washington Committee for Human Rights in Argentina records, 1964-2016 RL.11806
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Washington Committee for Human Rights in Argentina records
1964-2016, bulk 1973-1986
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Washington Committee for Human Rights in Argentina
RL.11806
9.1 Linear Feet
The Washington Committee for Human Rights in Argentina operated in the late 1970s and early 1980s to advocate for the human rights of Argentines targeted during the Dirty War/El Proceso. The committee was formed by prominent Argentines who had resettled in the United States, especially in the Washington, D.C. area. The committee frequently partnered with other human rights organizations, including the Washington Office on Latin America, to sponsor programming and mailings to raise awareness of the situation in Argentina. The Washington Committee for Human Rights in Argentina records consist of correspondence, mailers, flyers, reports, notes, programming information, petitions, lists, pamphlets, newspaper clippings, poetry, photographs, posters, and journal articles.
Biographical / Historical
The Washington Committee for Human Rights in Argentina (WCHRA) was founded in 1977 following Argentine dictator Jorge Rafael Videla's rise to power and the beginning of the Proceso de Reorganización Nacional/National Reorganization Process. The committee raised awareness of human rights abuses in Argentina, circulated petitions, and collected testimonies of victims. They also dialogued with government officials as well as professional organizations to change their stances and policies on Argentina in light of human rights abuses perpetrated there. The committee consisted of Argentines living in the United States, mainly in Washington, D.C. The membership consisted primarily of educated professionals and academics including Tomas Gergely, Ana Lajmanovich, and Juan E. Méndez.
The committee often partnered with larger human rights organizations, including the Washington Office on Latin America and the Association Solidarite Franco Argentine (A.S.F.A). WCHRA largely became inactive by the mid-1980s.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Washington Committee for Human Rights in Argentina records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2019.
Related Materials
Marshall T. Meyer papers, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Juan Méndez papers, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book &amp Manuscript Library, Duke University
Patricia Murphy Derian Papers, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Memoria Abierta records, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Washington Office on Latin America records, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Jerome Shestack Papers, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Robert J. Cox papers, 1879-2010, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Collection Overview
The Washington Committee for Human Rights in Argentina records document its members' advocacy for the rights of Argentines and their efforts to document human rights abuses during the Dirty War/El Proceso. The collection comprises three series: the Administrative Files series, 1964-1984; the Publications series, 1965-1986; and the Subject Files series, 1973-2016. The Administrative Files series consists of the materials that directly document the work of committee members to do outreach and lobby government officials to support changes in U.S. foreign policy towards Argentina. The Publications series consists of full-length publications. The Subjects Files series consists of newspaper clippings, photographs, flyers from other organizations, posters, and wires. Materials are primarily in English and Spanish with some materials in French, Italian, and Portuguese.
Abuelas de Plaza de Mayo (Rosario, Santa Fe, Argentina); Disappeared persons -- Argentina; Human Rights -- Latin America; Human Rights -- Argentina; Journalism -- Political aspects; Madres de Plaza 25 de Mayo (Rosario, Santa Fe, Argentina); State-sponsored terrorism -- Argentina; Timerman, Jacobo, 1923-1999; Victims of state-sponsored terrorism -- Argentina; Washington Office on Latin America; Jews -- Argentina; Méndez, Juan E.; Gergely, Tomas E., 1943-; Human rights advocacy
- Administrative Files, 1964-1984; 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of working documents of WCHRA including information about events, internal memos, external correspondence, reports, programs, testimonies of victims, and documents from other organizations. The testimonies of victims were largely gathered by WCHRA members.
  - Events and Campaigns, 1979-1984 (Box 1)
  - International Solidarity Congress with Argentina, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Teresa Lajmanovich, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1976-1983 (Box 1)
  - Petition for Disappeared Scientists, 1982; 4 folders (Box 1)
    The folders consist of different versions of the petition regarding disappeared scientists distributed by the WCHRA, notes, and lists of names for the petition. Notable signatories include George Wald, Salvador Luria, and Noam Chomsky.
  - Reports and Testimonies, 1977-1984; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Notes and Resources, 1977-1981 (Box 1)
  - Testimonials, 1978-1983; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science: Reports and Correspondence, 1976-1984; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence from Academics and Scientists, 1976-1983 (Box 1)
  - Washington Office on Latin America, 1978-1983 (Box 1)
  - Patrick Rice and Religious Organizations, 1977-1981 (Box 1)
  - Madres and Abuelas de la Plaza de Mayo, 1978-1983 (Box 1)
  - Nobel Peace Prize Campaign - Adolfo Perez Esquivel, 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - Centro de estudios legales y sociales (CELS), 1981-1983 (Box 1)
  - Emilio Fermín Mignone, 1979-1981 (Box 1)
  - Report on Human Rights in Chile Americas Watch Committee, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Uruguay Solidarity, 1980-1983 (Box 1)
  - France Solidarity, 1977-1981 (Box 1)
  - Memos and Documents from Other HR Organizations, 1977-1982 (Box 1)
  - Solidarity in Other Countries, 1979-1983 (Box 1)
    Documents about solidarity efforts in Costa Rica, Grenada, El Salvador, Nicaragua, Bolivia, and Lebanon.
  - Asamblea Permanente de Derechos Humanos, 1977-1979 (Box 1)
  - Comittee for Human Rights in Argentina, 1976-1978 (Box 2)
  - Council on Hemispheric Affairs, 1978-1981 (Box 2)
  - Organization of American States, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Familiares de desaparecidos y detenidos por razones politicas, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Amnesty International, 1977-1981 (Box 2)
  - Christmas Cards, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Malvinas Campaigns, 1964-1982 (Box 2)
  - Mailers, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Violations of the Right of Asylum and Testimonies, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Testimonies and Information about Disappeared People, 1976-1981 (Box 2)
    Includes substantial information about disappeared children.
  - Boletins Informativos de La Direccion General de Prensa y Difusion, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Niños Desaparecidos en La Republica Argentina Desde 1976, 1978-1981 (Box 2)
  - Niños Desaparecidos en La Republica Argentina Desde 1976 (copy), 1978-1981 (Box 2)
  - Testimony on Secret Detention Camps in Argentina, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Argentine Information Service Center Partial List of Victims of Repression in Argentina, 1978 (Box 4)
  - List of Detained P.E.N., 1978 (Box 4)
  - Nomina Tentativa de Personas Desaparecidas en la Argentina Desde 1975 a 1978 Incluido, 1975-1978 (Box 4)
  - Permanent Assembly for Human Rights List of Disappeared, 1978 (Box 4)
  - WCHRA Stamps, undated (Box 8)
- Publications, 1965-1986; 2
  The Publications series consists of publications gathered by WCHRA members. The contents largely cover El Proceso/the Dirty War, the disappeared, human rights abuses, American foreign policy towards Argentina, scientists' responses to human rights abuses and Argentine Jews targeted during El Proceso/the Dirty War.
  - Amnesty International Report, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Argentina Outreach Bulletin of the Argentine Information Service Center, 1977-1979 (Box 2)
  - Boletin del CDA Comite por la Democracia en Argentina, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - Breve Historia de la Argentina, 1965 (Box 2)
  - CAS Report Bulletin of the Comision Argentina de Solidaridad, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - Clearinghouse Report on Science and Human Rights, 1980-1982 (Box 2)
  - Cuadernos C.T.P., 1982 (Box 2)
  - Educacion, Ciencia, Tecnologia y Subdesarrollo by Dr. Mauricio Schoijet, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Embassy of Argentina - Argentine Position with Respect to the Report Prepared by the Inter-American Commission on Human Rights, 1980 (Box 2)
  - General Pamphlets, 1977-1983 (Box 2)
  - General Periodicals and Reports, 1976-1986; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Humor, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Informe de Amnistia International Violacion de los Derechos Humanos en Colombia, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Informe Sobre la Situacion de los Derechos Humanos en Argentina, 1980 (Box 3)
  - La Semana, 1983-1984; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Latin America Economic Report, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
  - Latin America Political Report, 1978-1979; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Latin America Quarterly Index, 1977 (Box 3)
  - Latin America Regional Reports Andean Group, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Latin America Regional Reports Brazil, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Latin America Regional Reports Caribbean, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Latin America Regional Reports Mexico and Central America, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Latin America Regional Reports Southern Cone, 1979-1983 (Box 3)
  - Latin America Weekly Report, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Latin America Weekly Report, 1980; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Latin America Weekly Report, 1981; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Latin America Weekly Report, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Matchbox, 1982 (Box 3)
    Published by Amnesty International USA.
  - noti ciero Asamblea Permanente por los Derechos Humanos, 1980-1982 (Box 3)
  - Noticias de Argentina extractos de la prensa Argentina y extranjera, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Report of the Mission of Lawyers to Argentina, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Report of the Special Committee on Violations of the Human Rights of Parliamentarians, 1977 (Box 3)
  - Reports on Human Rights, 1977-1984; 3 folders (Box 3)
    The reports largely detail human rights in Latin America, the treatment of Argentine Jews during the Dirty War, or human rights advocacy work by professional scientific organizations.
  - Science and Human Rights Uruguay and the Southern Cone, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Scientific Publications, 1977-1984; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Scientists and Human Rights in Latin America, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Separata Movimiento Ecuménico por los Derechos Humanos (MEDH), 1978 (Box 4)
  - The Argentine Situation Concerning Human Rights, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Update Latin America, 1978-1982 (Box 4)
  - Uruguay, 1979-1982 (Box 4)
  - Women in Dialogue Inter-American Meeting, 1979 (Box 4)
- Subject Files, 1973-2016; 3
  The Subject Files series consists of newspaper clippings, flyers, posters, newsletters, drawings, photographs, poetry, magazine articles, and wires. Some of these materials were annotated by WCHRA members and appear to have been circulated among members.
  - Argentine Newspaper Articles, 1976-1980 (Box 4)
  - Book Proposal The Disappeared of Argentina, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Clippings from Westerkamp, 1979; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Congressional Record House of Representatives, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Drawing by Julio Alberto Carreras, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Gabriel Alejandro Cwilich, 1973-1979 (Box 4)
  - Horacio Alberto Castro Informe, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Intellectuals and students on Argentina, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - International Policy on Human Rights of International Federation of Social Workers, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Jacobo Timerman, 1984 (Box 4)
  - La Nación Clippings, 1981 (Box 4)
  - La Prensa and the Buenos Aires Herald Clippings, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Latin American book trade, 1978-1982 (Box 4)
  - Lists of Detained Clippings, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Look into the real Argentina, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Los Niños de Nuestra Patria, 1979 (Box 4)
  - Military and Human Rights Clippings, 1976-1977 (Box 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1976-1979; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1980-1982 (Box 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1983-1984 (Box 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Newspaper/Magazine Articles and Book Sections, 1977-1983; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Observaciones al Proyecto de Ley de Reformas al Codigo de Justicia Militar, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Personal Materials of Tomas Gergely, 1981, 2016 and undated (Box 5)
  - Photographs, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Poetry, 1977 (Box 5)
  - Press Clippings Inter American Development Bank, 1982-1983 (Box 5)
  - Rodolfo Walsh, 1977 (Box 5)
  - Science and Technology, 1979-1982 (Box 5)
  - Scientists - Human Rights, 1977-1982 (Box 5)
  - Somos familiares padres or tíos de niños desaparecidos en Argentina, 1981-1982 (Box 5)
    This pamphlet outlines stories of the disappearanced relatives of Osiris Dominguez, Mabel Castro de Dominguez, Marta Enseñat, Nelson Hernandez, Adolfo Luis Lopez Mateos, Jorge Nadal, Julio Ramirez, and Adalberto Eraldo Rossetti. It includes lists of facts about the disappeared, newspaper clippings about their cases, and personal statements from the relatives who created the pamphlet.
  - The Clinic of Hope Joelito Filártiga, 1982 (Box 5)
  - Una Experiencia Educativa Argentina Manuel Sadosky, 1980 (Box 5)
  - U.S. Magazine and Newspaper Clippings, 1977-1980 (Box 5)
  - Washington Post and New York Times Clippings, 1975-1980 (Box 5)
  - Wires, 1970s (Box 5)
  - Wires, 1981-1983 (Box 5)
  - Wires, undated (Box 5)
  - Newspaper Pages, 1977-1980 (Box 6)
  - Newspaper Pages, 1981-1984 (Box 6)
  - Posters, undated (Box 7)
  - Newspaper Pages, 1977-1980 (Box 7)
  - Newspaper Pages, 1981-1982 (Box 7)
  - List of Disappeared, 1981 (Box 7)
    Published in La Prensa.
  - Posters, 1978-1979 and undated (Oversize-folder 1)